<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A trumpet sounding an alarvm from the Spirit of Life through an inhabitant of the City of God to all the inhabitants of the earth. But most especially, to the rulers and inhabitants of the city of Exon: To the end, the dead may be raised, the deaf hear, the dumb speak, the lame walk, and the unclean spirit cast out, and the poor receive the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Bacon, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76644</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B266A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170418</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578129</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578129</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172090</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76644)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2613:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A trumpet sounding an alarvm from the Spirit of Life through an inhabitant of the City of God to all the inhabitants of the earth. But most especially, to the rulers and inhabitants of the city of Exon: To the end, the dead may be raised, the deaf hear, the dumb speak, the lame walk, and the unclean spirit cast out, and the poor receive the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer 1662,.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Christopher Bacon.</note>
                  <note>The second letter "n" of "inhabitants" in the caption title is upside-down.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172090:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUMPET SOUNDING AN ALARVM FROM THE SPIRIT of LIFE Through an Inhabitant of the City of GOD TO ALL The Inhabitants of the Earth.</p>
            <p>But moſt eſpecially, To the RULERS and Inhabitants of the CITY OF EXON: TO THE END, The dead may be raiſed, the deaf hear, the dumb ſpeak, the lame walk, and the unclean ſpirit caſt out, and the poor receive the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Yeer 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172090:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172090:2"/>
            <head>A Trumpet, ſounding an Alarms from the Spirit of Life, through an inhabitant of the City of God, to all the inhabitants of the Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AWake, awake, ariſe, ariſe, prepare, prepare, all you who are in, and under ſin; death and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have power over you; Oh! come away (ſtay not) to meet the Lord of Life (who is a Spirit) by faſting, weeping and mourning, who is come and coming to judge the quick and the dead, and this is the glad tydings of the Goſpel, which is the croſs of Chriſt, the power of God, that convinceth, condemneth and judgeth ſin in your mortal fleſh. Tremble and fear, and come down all you proud, high and lofty, ambitious, wanton ſons and daughters of men; you that live in pleaſures, are dead while you live, and cut off from the Land of the living, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you ſpeedily repent and forſake all your abominations, by which you have provoked the Lord to pour down his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon you. Oh! alas, alas, I am filled with the ſence of the wrath, anger and indignation of the Lord of Hoſts, whoſe dreadful day is at hand: Oh! howle and lament, waile and weep bitterly, bow down, put your mouths in the duſt, ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> off your filthy, polluted Harlots attire, and cloath you with ſackcloth, and wallow in aſhes, for <hi>Sodom</hi>'s ſins are multiplied in and amongſt you, and you are covered with a cloud of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and the ignorance of <hi>Nineveh</hi> hath overſhadowed you, who are wiſe to do evil, but to do good you know not how and whilſt you profeſs God, Chriſt, Faith and Scripture, you periſh for want of the knowledge of God, Chriſt, Faith and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172090:3"/> Scriptures. And Friends, this is the Word of the Lord to you all, Rulers, Judges, and all Officers, Biſhops, Deans, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Curates, Prieſts, and all people ſmall and great, high and low, rich and poor, bond and free, Except you return unto, and believe in the true Light of Jeſus Chriſt the Son of the living God, you wil periſh and dye, and never enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Heaven. Oh! come down ye uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in heart and ears, and lend an ear to hear him who is the good Shepherd, and the Light of the World, that light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every man that cometh into the World; for it is he onely who deſtroyeth him that hath the power of death (which is the Devil) who is the new and living way to God out of the fall and ſeparation which ſin hath made between you and God, which you all are in until you return to him, believe in, and follow him. Friends, this is no new nor ſtrange thing but to them that are alienated from the life and knowledge of God. Oh! Rebel no longer againſt the light, as the generation of old did in <hi>Job</hi>'s days, who ſaid, <hi>God depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes;</hi> for it is the true Light that ſhineth in your dark hearts, which you in the darkneſs cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, till you receive, and love it, and are led by it, that muſt bring you all to the knowledge of God and his wayes, if ever you come to know it; <hi>for there is no man that knoweth the Father ſave the Son, and he to whom the Son ſhall reveal him;</hi> and this reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation or inſpiration giveth to all mankind that receive it, and wait in it, a right underſtanding, to know him that is true, the beginning of the Creation of God. Oh Friends! conſider be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, who ſay you believe in God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt; What are you come to witneſs of the power and coming of Jeſus Chriſt the holy and the juſt one? And what comfort have you in the Holy Ghoſt in your own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars? Is the Devil's Work deſtroyed in you, which is the cauſe of God's Wrath and Indignation? theſe branches as followeth, (which ſprung from the ſeed of the Serpent, and is brought forth by the Dragons power, and encouraged by the Whore and Beaſt) Murder, VVhoredom, Theft, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Lying, Curſing, Drunkenneſs, Covetouſneſs, Pride, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, Hereſie, Sedition, Strife, Envy, Fighting, Cheating, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zening,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172090:3"/> defrauding one another, greedily following luſt, in Bull-baiting, Cock-fighting, Hunting, Card-playing, Dice, Stage-playes, and other vain and ungodly practices, which are all the Works of the fleſh, brought forth under the power of death and darkneſs: Oh Friends! if theſe things be not deſtroyed in you by the power and coming of Jeſus Chriſt, you are without ſalvation by him, or comfort by the Holy Ghoſt, and dead to God, and crucifie Chriſt a freſh, and alive in your ſins, poſting on in the broad way, and are near deſtruction, whoſe portion is the Lake that burneth with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: Oh! lament and bow down you tall Cedars, repent and forſake your ſins, for the great and terrible day of the Lord God haſteneth; yea, in the Name and Fear of the Lord I proclaim it to you all, it is near at hand, a Day of fierce wrath, blackneſs and thick darkneſs, diſtreſs, gloomineſs and deſolation, is ſwiftly and irreſiſtably coming upon all the wicked and ungodly, that hate reproof, and make a mock at ſin, and will not take counſel of the Spirit of Life which hath long ſtriven with you; then you that are ſtrong and mighty, and truſt in the arm of fleſh, and carnal Weapons, Swords, Guns, Clubs and Staves; Oh! alas, alas, then fear, terror, weakneſs, amazement and aſtoniſhment ſhall ſeize upon you all, and the carnal Weapons of every evil-doer ſhall be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt his fellow; then ſhall the Kings of the Earth, the great men and the mighty men, the rich men and the chiefe Captains, cry unto the Rocks and to the Mountains to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and the clefts of the Rocks to hide them from the Wrath of the Lord, and of the Lamb, whom your forefathers with bloody hands crucified and killed the Prince of Life, and you their children are treading in the ſame ſteps, by ſhedding the blood, and perſecuting the Saints and faithful followers of Jeſus Chriſt; therefore you ſhall have blood to drink, and the cup of fury, wrath and indignation, muſt be poured forth upon you without mixture, if you repent not, and turn from all the evil of your ways, Oh Friends! why wil you dye? come to the beginning of the new Creation of God, and encline your ear to hear the ſaving Light of Chriſt, the faithful and true Witneſs of God which he hath placed in your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172090:4"/> which never conſented to your evil, and truſt not in ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vanities or precepts from the falſe Prophets, who have built you up in vain hopes, and have long cryed peace unto you, whilſt the ſword of the Lord hath reached unto your ſouls, and promiſe you life and ſalvation by Chriſt after this life; be it known unto you all, you have no aſſurance of life, peace, or ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt, until you are led by him, &amp; ſaved from your ſins, which was (before-mentioned) bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched forth in many particulars.</p>
            <p>So all come to the Witneſs of God in your conſciences, that will give you all a true and a certain evidence whether you are in the way of life or death, the ſtrait or the broad; and if the witneſs of God in your conſciences condemn you, you are not ſaved nor juſtified. Oh! Return, return to the true Light that will diſcover the ſecrets of your evil corrupted hearts, and the ſin and evil which is conceived in the Womb of darkneſs, and receive, believe in, and follow it's manifeſtation, that by it you may be led out of ſin, death and darkneſs; that's the way to peace, reſt, and aſſurance of eternal life; for in him who is the Light of the world; Life and Immortality dwells, and you cannot, nor ſhall not find it in any other way. Oh! Rebel no longer againſt that Spirit which hath, and doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove you in ſecret for your evil deeds, but receive its reproof, that your ſins may be mortified; this is the Spirit of God that is freely given unto you that you ſhould profit by it. And Friends, conſider, if you are not led by his Spirit to true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, love, goodneſs, godlineſs, holineſs, purity, ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, charity, meekneſs, you are not the children of God, though you may call God your Father, who is indeed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithful and upright in heart, becauſe you have loſt your firſt ſtate, and are enemies to God by reaſon of wicked works, and are not reconciled by Chriſt, and redeemed out of the fall, and renewed again in his Image, but are led by the ſpirit of Antichriſt, which hath reigned over all the world ſince the dayes of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, in the dark night of Apoſtacy, and great perverſion from the right way; this ſpirit cryes damnable Doctrine; the whole world hath been deceived with ſhadows without the ſubſtance; death hath been
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172090:4"/> ſet up inſtead of life, the form of godlineſs without the power thereof. Oh! why will you alwayes go aſtray? Will you never think upon your latter end? Except you live the life of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, you cannot be bleſſed in your death: Oh! ſeek no longer the living among the dead, for that which may be known of God is manifeſted in you; the time of this great ignorance God winked at; but now he calleth all men every where to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, becauſe he hath appointed a day in which he wil judg the world in righteouſneſs by that man Chriſt, who hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced you of your unrighteouſneſs; oh! flight not this day of his tender viſitation, who would have gathered your fore-fathers who periſhed in their diſobedience; the like deſtruction wil come upon you, if you go on in rebellion againſt him: Oh! whileſt he knocks at the doors of your hard hearts, with ſpeed open unto him, and receive him who is the Mediator of the New-Covenant with God, that in this your day and time you may know the things that concern your peace before they be hid from your eyes, and your eye utterly darkened, never more to perceive, and ſo to periſh and dye with the uncircumciſed: Oh! bow down, hear and feas the living God who created all men, to the end he might be glorified in them, and take delight in the work of his own hand.</p>
            <p>Tremble all you who live in pride, luſt, wantonneſs and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who eat and drink, and riſe up to play; oh! you have forgot the Lord your Maker, you have greatly diſhonored him, and have and do ſpend, waſte and conſume his good creatures upon your luſts, whereby you have greatly kindled the anger of the juſt God againſt you; you are like the fatted Bullock who is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſlaughter, and knoweth not whither he is going; even ſo the day of the Lord (as travel upon a woman) will overtake you, and when you cry to your ſelves peace and ſafety, then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, wo and miſery ſhall come rouling in upon you like the irreſiſtible waves of the ſea; Oh then ſhall your greateſt joys be your greateſt torments; the ſongs of your Temples turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into howlings, your laughter into weeping, and all the glory, pleaſure, beauty, friendſhip that you have in the world, ſhal then depart from you: Alas, alas, what tongue can expreſs the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, wo, grief and pain that the wicked and ungodly muſt then
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172090:5"/> partake of, out of it then there will be no redemption; a fire ſhall be kindled in your luſt, which will for ever burn, and none ſhall quench it, except you ſpeedily and unfeinedly repent, and forſake all your evil wayes, which is the cauſe of Gods, wrath againſt you; which never will depart from you, until you receive the only begotten Son of God, whom he hath freely given, to reconcile the World unto himſelf: And Friends all this know, that all they who are reconciled to God by Chriſt, do ceaſe from ſin, and can live no longer therein, nor have fellowſhip with them that live therein; and ſo Gods wrath comes thereby to be removed: and that is the way to Eternal Life and Peace. Oh <hi>England, England,</hi> (but eſpecially the Citty of <hi>Exon</hi>) what La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation ſhall I take up? or how ſhall I bewail the Rulers, Governours, Judges, Magiſtrates, Biſhops, Deans, Doctors, Chapters, Curates, Prieſts of all ſorts, who profeſſe your ſelves Chriſtian Rulers, and Miniſters of Juſtice; oh that ever you ſhould be ſo far degenerated from the juſt Precept, and holly Ordinance of ſound Judgment: Friends, the Ordinance of God I dearly own, and my ſoul is ſubject to it, as it is brought forth, and executed in the power of God, which is the higheſt power, which ſaith, do juſtly, and love mercy, paſſe Right and ſound Judgment in every cauſe, without reſpect of perſons, that your ſword may be a terror to every evil work, to ſuppreſſe and weaken vice, and the hand of every evil doer; and to encourage, and ſtrengthen, and protect in peace all that do well; which we whom you perſecute, and ſhamefully intreat, reproach, and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully call Quakers, do earneſtly pray for, and greatly deſire to ſee, the Rulers, Governours, Judges, and all Magiſtrates to come into, and be eſtabliſhed in the higheſt power, that is, the Power of God, which was and is ordained to that end, for the puniſhment of evil doers, and not againſt the Righteous: and oh Friends, as you rule in this, you will honour the living God in your time, and be truly honourable in your Generation: then the Nations round about you will hear of your fame, and the Generations of the Righteous to come, will call you the bleſſed of the Lord: But oh alas, alas I may ſay, as the Prophet did, <hi>True judgment is turned away backwards, and juſtice ſtands afar off; truth falleth in the ſtreets, and equity cannot enter: And he that feareth God, and departeth from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172090:5"/> iniquity, is become a prey,</hi> to the men of this Generation, and are afflicted, perſecuted and impriſoned.</p>
            <p>Come Biſhops, Deans, Doctors, Chapters, Curates, Prieſts of all ſorts, who have long ſaid, you are Miniſters of Chriſt, Miniſters of the Goſpel; come forth, and prove your Call and practice by your Life and converſations, to concurre and agree with the Life, Doctrine, and practice of Jeſus Chriſt, and his Miniſters; for the day is come, <hi>that the day ſtar is ariſen,</hi> and the glorious Light ſhineth out of the darkneſſe, which gives us who are raiſed in it, a true and a right diſcerning, whereby we are come to try your ſpirits, and have found it to be the ſpirit of Antichriſt, and falſe Prophet in the ſheeps cloathing, but in the woolviſh nature, making havock of the Flock of Chriſt, and are this day found to have a hand in the perſecution of the people of the Living God, whom you ſcornfully call Quakers, by ſtirring up the Magiſtrates, and incenſing the Rulers againſt us, by many falſe Accuſations, as your Fore-fathers (the Chief Prieſts) did againſt the juſt one, Jeſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and faithfull Servants.</p>
            <p>Come, where received you this Goſpel, who preach up blood, ſtrife, baniſhment, and perſecution? this doth not concurre, nor agree with the Goſpel, and Doctrine, and practice of Chriſt, and his Diſciples, whoſe Goſpel and Doctrine, practice, and good Examples, brought, and wrought in the true Chriſtans, in the Primitive dayes, as it doth now amongſt us who are in the ſame faith, and worſhip in the ſame way, Glory to God, peace on earth, and good will to all men, which is the fruit and mark of a true Chriſtian. Come let us reaſon a little together in this particular, whether you could willingly receive ſuch meaſure of cruelty from us, or any other in Authority, to ſhed your blood, be baniſh'd, ſhut up in cloſe Priſons, ſpoiling of goods, not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring your Friends to come to viſit you, but whip, keep upon guard, retain in priſon, them, for ſo doing: Surely Chriſt never teacht you this thing; but this is the Doctrine of the Devil, who is come in great rage, to deſtroy the workmanſhip of God, that the ſpiritual wickedneſſe may reign, without controle; neither is it agreeable with the Life, Doctrine, and Diſcipline of the Apoſtles, whoſe weapons were not carnal, but ſpiritual, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172090:6"/> mighty through God, to the breaking down of the ſtrong holds, and wreſtled not with fleſh and blood neither went about to deſtroy the Creatures, neither compelled any by force to hear their Goſpel; but in all Godlineſſe, gentleneſſe, and meekneſſe of ſpirit, wreſtled with the ſpiritual wickedneſſe, which hath, and doth make the ſeparation between God and the Creature.</p>
            <p>And Friends, think not in your mindes to bring us, whom the Lord God by his power hath redeemed, and gathered out of your formal, dead, will-worſhips, by the ſtrength, force, and cruelty, by your carnal weapons, ſwords, guns, clubs, whips, ſtocks, and ſtones, Baniſhment, nay verily, we can rather give up our lives until we ſee a thorow Reformation, and Converſion, wrought by the power of God in you, and ſeparated from all your abomination; and the fruits of Chriſt, and his holy Apoſtles, brought forth in you all; and verily, verily you can no more bring us back to your dead Worſhips again; you may as well ſtop the Sun in his line, or keep back the Waves of the Sea in its courſe, as bring us, which you ſcornfully call Quakers, into Bondage again, who are raiſed up in the knowledge of the living God, his holy wayes and worſhip, which is in his own Spirit and Truth, which makes free from ſin and death: we can no longer go with you, to ſeek the Living amongſt the dead, which you are all in, who do not believe in, and follow the the Light of Jeſus Chriſt, and know not what ſpirit you are of, though you profeſſe your ſelves Chriſtian Rulers, Chriſtian Miniſters, and Chriſtian People, and ſay, If you had been in the dayes of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, you would not have crucified Chriſt, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted his holy Apoſtles, and ſhamefully intreated the true Chriſtians: Oh Friends, ſeriouſly conſider, whether you are not doing the very ſame thing to us, who are members of Chriſt; you are at this day ſhedding our blood, whipping, ſtocking, ſtoneing, ſcourging in your Synagogues, haleing before Magiſtrates, caſting into Priſons, not ſuffering our Friends freely to come unto us, but we are retained in priſon; and one Woman was whipt for coming to viſit us, whereof this City of <hi>Exon</hi> in the County of <hi>Devon,</hi> may witneſſe: Oh hear, and be inſtructed all you Rulers, judges, Governours, and Magiſtrates, Biſhops, Deans, Doctors,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172090:6"/> Chapters, Prieſts, and all People; but eſpecially the Rulers, Biſhop, and Inhabitants of the City of <hi>Exon,</hi> in fear and with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding read <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. Oh what will you do in that day, when the King of Heaven and Earth ſhall ſit upon his Throne of Glory, who will make a ſeparation between the <hi>bleſſed</hi> and the <hi>curſed,</hi> and <hi>will ſay to the curſed on his left hand, I was hungry and ye gave me no meat, thirſty, and ye gave me no drink, naked, and ye cloathed me not, a ſtranger, and ye took me not in, ſick, and in priſon, and ye viſited me not; therefore depart ye curſed into everlaſting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> Oh Friends, betime, before your day is over, and viſitation paſt away, put a ſtop to your cruel Perſecution, leaſt you bring all <hi>the blood of the righteous, from righteous Abel to this preſent day,</hi> upon your heads; the cry thereof will remain unto the third and fourth Generation. Oh ſit down and conſider, the blood-thirſty ſhall not eſcape the juſt judgment of the Lord, neither the wicked Perſecutors ſhall live out half their dayes: remember the <hi>Sodomites, Pharaoh,</hi> and the reſt of the Perſecutors of old, whom the Lord God deſtroyed by his Eternal power, which will aſſuredly overtake you, except you repent: and take counſel of his Son, who ſaith, <hi>Touch not mine anointed, nor do my Prophets no wrong;</hi> he is the Fountain of all Wiſdome; he is our wonderfull Counſellor, <hi>and the author and finiſher of our Faith,</hi> in which we have and ſhall overcome the World, and outlive all our Perſecutors; not by carnal weapons, ſword, ſpear, nor bow, nor ſtrength by hoſte of men, or arm of fleſh, but by our keeping the Word of God, the <hi>ſword of the ſpirit, the armour of Light, and the teſtimony of Jeſus Christ,</hi> and in his faith and patience, we have and ſhall ſuffer, and bear all things for his names ſake, till he ſhall ariſe, upon whom is laid, for us to plead our innocent cauſe; then ſhall all our Enemies and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors be aſhamed, and condemned, be droven backwards, and fall into the pit, which they have digged for the innocent: Oh, while you have time, reform your wayes, and glorifie God, by bringing forth of fruit by a holy life; or elſe he will be glorified in your deſtruction: Oh conſider what you are a doing; oh when will you ſit down and remember your latter end, whiles the ſpirit of the Living God ſtrives with you! oh rebel no longer againſt it, leſt you periſh in your gainſaying; oh ariſe, ariſe you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172090:7"/> that are aſleep in the duſt of the earth; this is not your reſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is poluted: Oh the day of account draws near, when the Lord God will plead with all fleſh, by his <hi>ſword, and with fire, which proceeds out of his mouth, by which he will ſlay his enemies in the valley of ſlaughter, and the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many:</hi> Oh then the Glory, the pleaſure, the beauty, friendſhip, and riches, and delights of this World ſhall ſoon come to an end, and ſhall be no more; and this is the word of Truth, an account muſt you all give unto the impartial juſt God, when the ancient of dayes ſhall ſit and judge, <hi>from whoſe face the heavens and the earth ſhall fly away,</hi> and all <hi>the wicked and ungodly ſhall be as a rolling thing before a fierce whirlwinde, or as ſtubble fully dry for the unquenchable fire,</hi> who will then without reſpect of perſons, title, or name of greatneſſe in the earth, judge and reward every one according to their works; <hi>then the righteouſneſſe of rhe righteous ſhall be upon him, and the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe of the wicked ſhall be upon him, and the ſoul that ſinneth ſhall ſurely dye:</hi> Therefore yet while you have the time, prize it, and return to the Light of Chriſt, which is the new and the <hi>living way, that your ſoules may live in rest and peace,</hi> (which is the deſire of my heart) when this World ſhall be no more: And this to you all, in the motion of Gods Spirit, and in bowels of tender love to your ſoules, is written, one warning more, before the Decree of the Lord God is ſealed againſt you, when time ſhall be no longer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>From a Servant of the Lord, and a faithfull follower of the Lamb, in the tribulations; and who prayes for good Governours, and Government, and a real Friend to Juſtice, who now ſuffers in outward bonds for the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Word of God, in the</hi> high Goal <hi>at</hi> Exon, <hi>known to you by the name of</hi> CHRISTOPHER BACON. But I have <hi>a new Name,</hi> for which you perſecute me.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>The</hi> 19th <hi>of the</hi> 9th Month. 1662.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
